OK let's get it started.
Hello everyone, welcome back to another lecture in Digital Design Computer Architecture.
I'm Muhammad and the Co instructor in this course.
Professor Mutu is travelling to USA to attend the conference.
So finally I got this opportunity to teach some of the lectures which I'm quite excited about.
Today we're going to start discussing about how we can implement micro architecture.
And we're going to start with actually one of the naive way or simple way of implementing micro
architecture, which is single cycle processor.
And then through the next week, we were going to be on top of it and do a better job by designing
multi cycle and also hopefully pipeline processor design.
So it's going to be basically the agenda for today and next few lectures, which you can see that
today we're going to start with micro architecture, some principles and also we're going to get to
single cycle micro architecture.
So here are also some readings for you.
We're going to actually use some of these readings.
There are some slides that I'm going to refer you also for more readings if you're interested, if
you can check to back and provide more deep understanding.
But at some point, as we go more and with modern processor design, we're going to also diverge from
these books.
Unfortunately, these books do not do a good, do not do a good job for modern processors essentially.
So we're going to get to that also later, maybe after, yeah, not next week, but the week after and
hopefully after the Easter break.
So this is a kind of recall just to jog your memory.
So implementation of the ISA under specific design constraints and goals, anything done in hardware
without exposure to software.
So that's a micro architecture.
And basically we can do a lot of different techniques in the micro architecture.
As as long as you can actually make sure that you don't exposure that to the software, things are
OK.
So as long as you can follow the phone Newman model essentially.
So now that we know what an ISA is, we can ask this question, how do we implement it?
Basically, how do we design a system that obeys the hardware software interface?
And also here is a site that remember about the yesterday lecture that we discussed about semantic
gap.
So essentially the ISA, it can be also in kind of a system design.
So it doesn't need to be always, you know the ISA which can be implemented immediately with the
hardware.
So there can be also some middle ISA which you translate the software to that middle ISA and that
middle ISA needs to be translated to some low level ISA which going to be executed in the hardware.
So basically you can check the yesterday lecture about translation of IS as and an ISA can be
converted by software or hardware into an implementation ISA.
However, we will assume completely hardware implementation for most lectures.
So, but don't forget about this side because most of the modern processors that we have today, they
are actually following these things that there are different levels of ISA that the processor is
working on it.
OK, so let me ask this question first that what does processing and instruction mean actually?
So we will assume the the one human model for now.
Essentially we have this terminology architectural state or AS which is the programmer visible state
before an instruction is processed.
And then essentially we process some instruction in the hardware which will get us to another state
which is AS prime architectural or programmer visible state after an instruction is processed.
So processing an instruction essentially means that how we transfer from AES to AES prime according
to the ISA specification of the instruction.
Here also some recall about phone human model which I guess you all know about it at this point.
So a store program and sequential instruction processing and there are different essentially units
in phone human model in order to keep the program a visible state like remember we need the memory,
we need registers and also program contract to make sure that we can keep the sequence of the
instructions.
So the process instruction step actually involves based on the ISA first.
So ISA specifies abstractly what AS prime should be given an instruction and the AS so essentially
ISA.
Defines an abstract finite state machine.
You can think about it as a similar to FSM, but state here are the programmer visible state.
So you have a, let's say for each program you can think about it as a big FSM and from one state to
another state.
Essentially you are trans.
Basically you're transitioning based on the instruction that you're executing.
So states are the programmer visible state and next state logic is essentially instruction that
you're executing your hardware.
So from ISA point of view, there are no intermediate states between a S&AS prime.
So basically from the programmer view and also compiler view, you only see that you move from one
state to another state which is still a programmer visible.
But there might be many intermediate states between that in the hardware which is completely hidden
to the programmer.
And that's how actually makes makes us how to implement micro architecture.
So in micro architecture, basically there are many choices and we can have programmer invisible
state to optimise the speed of the instruction execution.
Essentially we can have multiple state transitions per instruction, but these are smaller let's say
states.
So one choice is that we can move from immediately from AS to AS prime in the hardware as well.
So essentially that's makes us makes us having a micro architecture which is single cycle.
So you everything you execute each instruction will take exactly 1 cycle.
So there is no, let's say, middle states or hidden states to the program.
But there are also another choices that you can actually move from architectural state to another
middle state, which is architectural state plus micro architecture state one.
And then from that state to another state and then from that state to another state.
And until you get to AS prime, which is the programmer visible view.
And this is something which is actually much more, I guess, familiar to your eyes.
Remember the the FSM that Professor Mutu showed you for LS LC3 execution?
There were several steps, for example for only fetching, fetching the instruction and then different
after decoding.
We had different states like essentially until they executed program.
But that FSM is not actually the FSM which is program and visible.
It's the FSM which defines for the micro architecture how we handle the execution of instructions.
So if you remember and you check that slide, you can also understand this part better.
OK, So we're going to see actually.
So in this lecture, we're going to mostly focus on choice one.
I'm going to have some size that I will work more deeply in the trade off between choice one and
choice 2.
But mostly we're going to build the computer, build the processor micro architecture based on the
choice one.
But next week we're going to get to choice, the second choice, which is much more, let's say, which,
which is a much better decision to make when you want to design the processor.
OK.
So as I said, a very basic instruction process engine, each instruction going to take single cycle
to execute.
And we're going to consider that only combinational logic is used to implement instruction
execution.
So in order to make sure that you don't have any cycles in between, you need to have everything
combinational.
Of course, there might be there, there should be some registers memory that they're going to be
updated at the right edge of the clock.
But other than that, everything is combinational, meaning that when you want to fetch instruction,
you need to do it in a combinational manner.
When you want, after fetching, you want to decode it, it should be also combinational.
After decoding, you access the register file, it should be combinational and then you execute it
should be combinational.
So everything is combinational because you don't want to cycle execution, you don't want to have
cycles in between of of this architectural estate.
We're going to see that with a with a lot of details later on as well.
So essentially we move from AS to AS prime with only one is cyclog cycle in the hardware.
OK, So this actually implementation is actually you can remind it.
You can also would can remind you this design of the sequential logic that essentially we have a
sequential logic state, which is the architectural state that we have currently.
And then you have some combinational logic in order to generate AS prime.
And so essentially you use current architectural estate with some input and then you process it with
your combinational logic and then you generate the next step.
So there are no, there is no, let's say registers, flip flops.
They were in between the like for the combinational logic here to make sure that you can do
everything in one cycle.
So now the question is that what's the clock cycle trying determined by which you already know
actually from from the timing lecture.
Did did you have a question or no?
So essentially if you remember from the timing lecture we were discussing about, we need to know the
critical pass latency, what's what's the longest pass that we have in our design That would be
determine the that would determine the the clock cycle of your design.
So, so here another way around asking this question in this context is actually what's the
essentially the longest delay pass.
So you have different instructions to implement.
I'm going to see that also.
So different instruction would have different delays because they are actually working on different
steps or stages of the of the process architecture.
So for example some instruction are accessing the memory in order to load data and then move it to
the register, right?
So these instructions clearly are much Stewart compared to a simple instruction like XOR OR and NAND
or these logical boolean logical instructions.
So in this design, if you have single cycle processor, you need to actually consider the longest
delay.
So essentially what would be the instruction that takes the longest delay?
And then based on that, you need to tune your clock cycle essentially.
And that's would actually give you some intuition that why this single cycle micro architecture is
not a good idea.
Because in the end, for all these instruction, you need to really wait for the longest delay
instructions.
We're going to get to that also a lot in future slides, but I just wanted to also foreshadow a
little bit now.
OK.
I also like to mention that nothing here is actually magic now for you because we already covered
this sequential logic state.
So you know how exactly they are built from the flip flops we made registers and also you have very
good understanding of combinational logic from the previous lectures.
So if when you look at the single cycle micro architecture and you see that it's actually considered
the combination logic and also sequential logic, now you're going to see that OK, it's not a magic.
But if you start, for example, the course from this slide, then it's might sound a little bit magic.
There is a still some magic which we couldn't cover, of course, that's how, for example, transistors
exactly operate based on the electronic principles.
But for that you need to take some other courses like electronic design courses, of course.
OK, sounds good.
So let me go over go over again a little bit about single cycle machine and multi multi cycle
machines to give you some more idea about it.
They're going to, these are actually going to be kind of a recap for you, but in single cycle,
essentially each instruction takes a single clock cycle and all the states, all the state updates
made at the end of the instruction execution.
So there is a big disadvantage here that the slowest instruction determines cycle time.
So we're going to have a long clock cycle time.
However, in multi cycle machines instruction processing broken into multiple cycles or stages, an
estate updates can be made during an instructions execution.
So there are some middle estate with some registers that you can think of and then essentially you
can update those estates.
Remember, these estates are not visible to the programmer, but they are useful to having the
hardware in order to make sure that you don't have that long clock cycle time.
But still in multi cycle machines, architectural estate updates, architectural estate updates made
at the end of an instructions execution.
So there is a big advantage over a single cycle with multi cycle machine that the slowest stage
here, the slowest stage determines cycle time.
So you can think of, OK, I, I want to have a processor with the clock frequency of 10 gigahertz.
And then you, you, you need to make sure that all the stages that you have in your micro
architecture should be done in for with that 10 gigahertz frequency, clock frequency.
Whereas in the single cycle machine you don't have that freedom.
Essentially, you can.
Basically you have some instructions based on the ISA that you need to support and your clock cycle
should be actually quite low enough to make sure that you can accommodate for the slowest
instruction that you have.
Even if that instruction is only, let's say one person of all instructions that you might have in
your program, your pipeline is still your micro architecture still needs to accommodate for that
slow instruction.
But both of them single cycle and multi cycle machines, they literally follow the von Newman model
at the micro architectural level.
So still there from the programmer perspective, things are the same.
Well, programming with the experience, different performance from the hardware, but terms of the
semantics and correctness of the execution, everything's going to be the same.
So basically, we have instruction processing cycle at the micro architecture, which I think you know
about it also from the previous lectures that essentially we need to do some sequence of the steps
to process an instruction.
And fundamentally, there are 6 steps.
Basically we fetch instruction, we decode instruction and then then we need to evaluate the
addresses, we fetch operands, we execute and then we need to store the result.
So these are 6 fundamental steps that you can think of for executing instructions.
So in a single cycle processor, all these fetch, decode, evaluate, fetch operands, execute and store
should take one cycle.
Whereas in multi cycle you can actually have several cycles for fetching, then several cycles for
decoding, several cycles for evaluating and so on and so forth.
Yeah, yeah, I already covered this.
So all six phases in single cycle would take only one cycle, but in multi cycle they can have
different cycles.
Any question.
Very good.
OK.
Yeah.
Just to also give you another perspective, instruction processing, basically instruction transfer,
transfer data to data prime.
So essentially you have some input data and and then you want to operate on those data and then
generate data prime.
Because in the end we process data, you know in our hardware.
So this transformation is done by functional units, so units that they operate on data.
You can think of for example ALU that you do some calculation on your data and there are also
basically these units that they operate on the data, they needs to be told what to do on the data.
So an instruction processing engine consists of two fundamental components.
1 is datapaths which is it consists of hardware elements that deal with and transfer data signals.
So in database you can think of functional units that operate on data like ALU.
You can think of hardware structures like wires, multiplexer, decoder, Tri set buffers that enable
the flow of data into the functional units and registers.
And also you can think of a storage unit that is stored data like registers.
OK.
However, all these units needs to be told what to do, and then that's the job for the control logic,
which consists of hardware elements that determine control signals.
Which signals that the specify what the data pass elements should do to the data essentially.
So whenever we want to design A processor micro architecture, we need to essentially design data
pass first and then based on the data pass we try to basically we do the control design.
So we generate basically control signals to make sure that our data pass can can be controlled
nicely to execute all these instructions.
So this slide is actually from LC3 that you have seen it also before we didn't cover it actually in
detail and we're going to see more later because this actually LC 3 is a multi cycle system.
It's an interesting design.
It's not single cycle, but just to give you some perspective here, there are a lot of units that you
can see here that they are actually related to the datapaths, which is like this program contract
is multiplexer.
All these wires register file AL us and many, many other things instruction register.
But there is also this finite esteem machine that generates controlled signals.
And if you check actually in this picture, you can see that those signals that they have black arrow
at the end, they're actually showing data pass signals.
And those signals that they have white arrow at the end, I know I don't, I'm not sure if it's quite
visible here, but these are white arrow, they are actually showing control signals.
So with that, you can actually distinguish nicely between the control signals and data pass signal
in this LC3 design.
We're going to get to that also much more in the future lecture when we go.
Go to multi cycle processor.
OK, so in single cycle, essentially control signals are generated in the same clock cycle as the one
during which data signals are operated on.
Because you cannot do any cycle right?
So you fetch instruction and then you decode the instruction and based on the decoding you need to
do, you need to generate these control signals and everything should be actually serialized in
order to run your instruction.
However, in multi cycle, you can actually, you can generate control signals in the next, basically
control signals that they're going to be needed in the next cycle.
You can generate them in the current cycle, which with that you can actually hide some latencies of
generating control signals, which gives you another level of priorities.
We're going to see that more also in the future lectures.
Also, if you're impatient, you can also check this appendix in Pat and Patl.
OK, so there are many ways of designing the datapath and control logic.
By now you I guess you know that we can design single cycle, multi cycle.
We're going to see pipeline processor.
So essentially the the our strategy and methodology is that we're going to start with single cycle.
We will explain it in detail and then we're going to see that basically analyse it.
We will analyse the performance of it.
And then we conclude with the weaknesses of this.
And then we ask the question that can we do better?
And hopefully in the next lecture we're going to see multi cycle design.
And then after that we're going to also evaluate it.
And then we want to do better.
And then we get to pipeline processor.
And after that, we're going to also do more and get to out of order data pass, which gives you
actually the cutting edge more or less of modern processors that we have today's.
Most of them are completely like out of order, which is actually quite interesting that we can we
can actually learn about what is happening today's in our systems.
Also you can think of having a single processor bus or multiple bus.
So here in this picture, you can see that there is this processor bus which is only one.
So there is only one bus which you know works there with the with the memory and also the processor.
So you can think of OK we want to have multiple buses to provide parallelist but then when you have
multi bus data pass you need to control it also.
So that would make also the control logic a bit more complicated.
Also from the control logic you can think of having it hardware or combinational like.
So everything they the the control logic generates control signal using some combinational circuits
which is hard wired or you can think of micro coded micro programme control like having some memory
with in that memory you can based on the instruction you basically look up in that memory and then
you get the control signals.
So most of the processors today are actually a combination of both.
So you have hardware control signals and also you have micro coded micro programme control.
We're going to get to that hopefully in the in the next week as with about micro programme control,
OK.
But the important thing here is that control signals and a structure, they depend on the data pass
design.
So that's why we always start with the data pass design.
And after finishing it completely, we make sure that now we can design the control signals in order
to make sure that the whole, the data pass can work correctly to execute every, all the
instructions that we have.
OK, so we're going to design different processors and then we're going to do some performance
analysis.
So I just want to foreshadow a little bit here.
It's important to understand how, what would be, let's say, one of the metric in order to analyse
performance.
So that's why it's kind of a flash forward here.
But in the end, one of the important metric here is that we want to see how fast we can execute the
program, right.
We do also care about other metrics like energy consumption, power consumption area, cost of the
processor.
But for for this slide, for this lecture, for sure, we don't get to that energy or power much more.
So for the performance analysis, execution time of single instruction is actually you can determine
by this CPI which is abbreviation of cycles per instruction like how many cycles you spend to
execute one instruction times clock cycle time which is which makes sense, right?
So your clock cycle time might be, let's say 1 nanosecond, meaning that your clock frequency is 1
gigahertz and then.
One instruction CPI in in a single cycle processor, for example, CPI is always one, right?
So then it means that execution of single instruction would take one nanosecond.
But in multi cycle processor there might be different CPI based on the instruction that you're
doing.
So that's why it's important to have this CPI here, so that CPI times clock cycle time, gives you
the execution time, execution time of a single instruction.
And then you want to execute, calculate the execution time of an entire program, which hopefully
your program have much more than one instruction.
And for that, you need to see all the dynamic instructions that you're executing.
I'm actually saying talking about dynamic instructions, because in your code you have branches, you
have loops, which in the end your dynamic instructions might be a lot more compared to the static
number of instructions that you can count, you know, in your code.
So in the end, we need to know how many instructions we have executed.
So then we can sum over all instructions, CPI times, clock cycle time.
So you know the execution time of each instruction and then you just sum it up.
Or in other words, you can think of having in this equation that execution time of a processor or
execution time, sorry execution time of a of a program, entire program on a processor.
You can calculate it based based on number of instructions, times average CPI and then times clock
cycle time.
So I'm talking about average CPI here because especially for multi cycle, it is important because
some instructions takes 3 cycles, some 4, some 5.
And then depending on the frequency of them, you're like how frequent they are in your code, you can
actually calculate average CPI and then based on that you can calculate the execution time.
So just to give you some perspective, number of instructions actually can be very much different.
So this equation actually gives you different ways of how to optimise the performance.
So you can actually reduce the number of instructions by better algorithms, for example.
So if you know for example, big O notation in software, essentially you can for sorting algorithm,
for example, you it can be NS square big O.
And then with that you have a lot of instructions, but you can actually reduce it to N log N for
example, you know with some quick sort, Med store or other sorting algorithm.
So with that you can actually reduce your number of instructions.
Another thing which is affecting your number of instructions is actually the ISA.
Sometimes your ISA is so at the very, very low level, at the very hardware hardware level, which
means that when you want to translate, the compiler wants to translate your high level code to the
machine code.
It needs to generate a lot of instructions.
Whereas in some processors, ISA is much more high level and then you're going to use, you're going
to have less number of instructions when you translate your code.
But that also would affect the average CPI.
So for example, there might be some processors that you have instruction of matrix multiply.
So you just in in order to instead of writing a code how to do this matrix multiplic, matrix matrix
multiplication, you have an instruction that you just write, I want to multiply this matrix to that
matrix.
Essentially you know there are actually processor like that.
So those processors.
So with that actually you are reducing the number of instructions that you have, but this
instruction will take much more number of cycles to be executed.
So here we actually you can see a trade off within the number of instructions and average CPI.
And then of course you have this clock cycle time which would affect how you design your micro
architecture.
So single cycle design is actually very, very bad in clock cycle time, which makes it quite long.
You can think of multi cycle design which you can reduce your clock cycle time.
So the your decisions at the micro architecture level would affect immediately the clock cycle time
as well.
So I'm not actually fully sure how it starts from the history.
I mean, that's a very good question actually to ask.
So I can definitely say that, you know, in the in the beginning the memories access latency much,
much, much more, much more closer to the access or let's say execution time of the processor.
So these were not that unbalanced.
So in that scenario.
So single cycle might make sense, but I should also say that I'm not, I'm not at least I'm not aware
of any processor that was single cycle.
So maybe it's actually more or less a design, you know, for, for the teaching perspective, because
we start with the single cycle and then we go to the multi cycle and then with the pipeline
processor.
But but at the same time also not sure.
So I will check it out and then we can discuss it later as well.
Yeah, there might be some processor in the past, but as far as I know most of them were multi cycle
to get from the get go.
Yeah, any other question?
OK.
So in single cycle market architecture performance, we know that CPI is always one by definition and
then clock cycle time is long.
In multi cycle CPI is different from each instruction and then average CPI should be hopefully
small.
We're going to see that with some analysis next week.
So your average CPI is going to be much of course greater than one, but we want to keep it small as
much as possible.
And then clock cycle time is short.
So The thing is that in multi cycle we have two degrees of freedom.
So we can play with the CPI and also the clock cycle time, right?
Whereas in single cycle micro architecture you don't have any freedom.
You say that, OK, this is my CPI one.
And then based on that, based on the instructions that you're supporting, that would essentially
that would determine your clock cycle.
So in the end, that's also another reason that why single cycle is not a good design to begin with
because you cannot optimise it well, you don't have that much freedom.
But that being said, it's a good thing to start with to learn about the topic because there are a
lot of fundamentals going on.
OK, any question?
So now we're going to start after this introduction, how we can design a single cycle market
architecture.
OK.
So it's a single cycle machine that we're going to build and then we're going to actually focus on
MIPS processor.
You actually you've seen MIPS assembly called also more or less and you're going to also use MIPS
assembly in your labs as well.
But in MIPS actually we have some state elements.
So we have actually program contour.
So that's it's, it's good to learn about this terminology because different processor, they might
have different naming as well like Intel X86, I think they were calling it instruction pointer IP.
But here in MIPS they call it program counter.
And this program counter is actually 5 bits.
Sorry, it's 32 bit, which so each instruction is yeah.
So you can actually exactly your, your instruction memory is 2 to the power 32.
And based on the amount that you stored in program counter, you can access your instruction memory
to get your instruction.
And each instruction is also 32 bits.
So with program counter, you store the address of the instruction and then you based on that you
access the instruction memory.
We also have register file which you also you know about it.
So here is MIPS.
So in MIPS we have 32 general registers.
So that's why we need 5 bits in order to, you know, provide the address to what register we want to
access.
And in MIPS also we have two basically read registers port and you have one right register port and
also write data.
So these are the address that you're doing.
So basically you provide, you can provide up to 25 bits in order to provide the address of those in
registers that you want to read from them.
And then you can also provide 5 bits address to the register that you want to write to it.
Also you need to provide write data which is 32 bits because registers are in MIPS are 32 bit.
And then you you also have two read read port as output that most of them are also 32 bit and based
on the address that you provide to the red register.
So the one that you provide to the red register one, you're going to get the data in read data one.
And the one that you provide the address to read register 2, you get the data in read data 2.
Makes sense, right?
And also you have this control signal which is read, write or Reg right which is in a.
It's a kind of a right enable.
So you so when you want to write your to your register file, you need to provide the right register,
the address, you need to provide the right data.
And also you need to assert this Reg right to make sure that such that you can write to your
register or update your register file at the rising edge of the clock.
Whereas in other ways, when you don't want to touch your register file, you need to make sure that
this control signal is always 0 to make sure that you don't cause any harm essentially.
Also in MIPS we have two different memory, instruction memory and data memory.
So instruction memory, essentially you provide the instruction address using the program counter and
then you get your instruction and data memory.
Essentially you provide the address again using the the address that you can calculate with the with
the some value of the register and also some immediate data, which we're going to also see.
And so that address can be used to specify if you want the the location that you want to read from
or the location that you want to update it.
So if you want to update, if you want to write to the memory, you need to provide the address and
also you need to provide the right data and you need to also assert membrite to write.
When you want to read from the memory, you provide the address and then you also need to assert
memory.
So this control signal is not absolutely needed because reading from the memory is not, at least
it's not harmful from the correctness problem, but it's good to have it in order to make sure that
when you really want to read from the memory, you activate the memory.
Otherwise, in order to save energy, for example, so we're going to use this notation in the lectures
there.
There are some different notations.
Your book also have more or less same notations.
But it's good to follow these notations to see to such that you can easily follow the lectures that
we're going to have.
And this also not new for you, a memory array.
Remember that we have this structure of four location 3 bits.
So in here in register file for example, we have 32 locations like 32 registers and each location is
32 bits.
But in this example it was it was 4 * 3.
And you know that you had this decoder in order to decode the right enable and also the the right
address or read address.
And then you also have this multiplexer in order to get the data out.
OK, yeah, these are also the the notation and pictures that they are in your book in which you can
check also.
But essentially it's more or less the same like program contrary is 32 bit register.
We have instruction memory which I already talked about it register file and also data memory.
Your book for example, does not consider this mem read.
But as I said, it's good to have it for energy optimization.
OK, so we're going to make some assumptions which they are not actually very good assumptions.
The first one actually we are considering when we want to design this single cycle processor, we are
considering ultra fast or let's say single cycle memory and register file.
Actually by saying single cycle, that doesn't mean that you need to wait for the whole cycle to get
your data.
Meaning that for example, if if my if my clock cycle is let's say 1000 picosecond, I should be done
by the memory read for example, in I don't know, like 300 picosecond.
And then we need to also we need to have some time for other stuff in the execution because reading
from the memory is not the only thing you're going to actually access your memory to get your
instructions.
So the fetch you know you're going to access the memory and then in the end also in some
instructions you might also need to load from the memory or you need to sort to the memory.
So those are going to also take some time.
So you need to make sure that everything can be done in your clock cycle.
So we are considering ultra fast memory and register fly.
We have a combinational read.
So output of the read data port is a combinational function which essentially you can you can think
of you access and then you have this big multiplexer which based on that you can select which
output you want to have like you know about the memory array.
So there is no let's say a sequential circuit when you want to read from your memory.
And also we have.
Synchronous, right, which we update the memories on also register file at the rising edge of the
clock which we which is important to make things correct.
OK.
And and then also we have single cycle memory, which we already talked about it there are.
But when the memory is actually not single cycle, we meaning that the latency that you might have
observed from the memory is actually different then actually like in the past processor were much,
I mean, currently also they are dealing with that.
So when you access the memory you want to read, that's a memory needs to work on your data, your
request and then provide basically a signal, which is ready signal indicate that the that the read
or write is done.
And then that signal gives you know and then processor can use that ready signal to do something
based on that.
So like in LC3B we have this for example ready signal which might which is useful there.
OK, so when we want to do the processing essentially we have we are considering 5 generic steps.
We do the instruction fetch, then we do the instruction decoding and register operand fetch.
So essentially, yeah, we come.
So remember that 6 steps that I talk about it here, we are actually combining the 2, the operant
fetch as and also decoding.
So decode and register operant fetch are considered at the at this stage and at this step.
And then the the next step is execute also evaluating the memory address.
So when you want to do some computation or calculation on your data, you need to do your executing.
But sometimes you want to generate the memory access address.
So with that also you are doing it at this step.
And then you can the next step is the memory operand fetch which we call it the memory, the mem
step.
And after that we have this store or write back result, which is the the last step.
So here is actually the the data pass that we are going to consider and then we're going to see how
we can make this work.
So you have this program counter and then you this program counter provides basically the address to
the instruction memory.
The instruction is fetched and then after fetching the instruction, you can access your register
file and the these read operands that you are getting out of the register file, they are going to
be calculated or going through the ALU.
And the output of the ALU might be used in order to store in the register file or use as an address
to access your data memory.
And the output of data memory might be also go to the register file in your some instructions.
So that's the data pass.
But this is not going to work.
Now we need to add a lot of logic to it to make it work.
But that's a fundamental way of thinking about data pass in these architecture because in the end,
you want to step to fetch, then you want to decode essentially, and then you want to do execution
and do address generators and memory and then write back.
So that's a, let's say it's quite, I mean, it's quite intuitive how we can implement the data pass.
But as I said, we need to add a lot of logic to make it work.
Any question about this slide?
Because we're going to build on it.
OK, very good.
So we need to provide the data pass and control logic to execute all ISA instructions.
And this is what we're going to get to through the end of this lecture, which may look a bit scary
at this moment, but we're going to see it's not actually that scary as we go through this lecture.
Is it actually very quite easy and intuitive.
So this is also another example, which is in your book, there are some differences between what
we're going to get to and what your book has.
Not a lot, but there are some differences.
For example, there is one this, yeah, this addition logic that we're going to have, we're going to
consider it because it's a good decision to do.
You're going to see also a lot why this is important to have this adding logic here.
But in your book, for example, there is so we have this addition and also another addition.
Here there are two addition logic, but your book consider only one addition and then the next
addition there the book.
Your book is doing it in the in the ALU OK.
So yeah, I think it's a good time to start and to have our break.
Let's get back at 3:15 and then we can start going over the single cycle database.
So so remember this structure.
Now we're going to see how we can add the logic suite to complete our datapaths such that it's
capable of running all the ISA instructions.
I mean, by saying all the instructions that we're going to show here, I mean MIPS ISA, even though
is actually still simple, but there are many, many instructions that we're not going to cover today
or in these lectures.
So that's why in the end, what we're going to get to is not going to be able to run everything that
MIPS has, but we'll give you enough understanding that how it's going to work.
And then after that, we're going to get to the control design, hopefully.
So 1st, we want to see how we can support our type ALU instructions.
So remember that in our type, we have three register operands.
Here's one example like addition of this register dollar S 0.
So, so this register is going to be the destination.
And then there are source registers that you're going to read them, add them and then a store to S0.
So there is a machine encoding of this instruction based on the machine code.
And we always use the formatting of the instructions.
So we have we need to use our type formatting.
And in our type, the machine code is like so OP code is always 0 because it's our type.
And then based on the, we need to set the function code to some number, which here is 32 to specify
that we want to do addition.
And then you need to put the register address based on this encoding, based on this formatting.
So we have this RSRT, these are the source registers and then we have this destination registers.
So the semantics of this instruction is that basically if the instruction is addition RDRRSRT,
basically the general purpose register Rd.
is going to be addition of these two registers and then we need to increment program contour by 4 in
order to get to the next instructions.
So that's also the semantics.
It's always important to know the semantics of the instruction because that gives you intuition how
to design the data password.
So in our design in this architecture in order to run this instruction.
So essentially here the instruction that we are reading from the instruction memory, we know that
the address 25 to 21 is going to be one of the source instruction Rs.
So that's why instruction 25 to 21 is going to be the read address of this one.
And then instruction for the RT is going to be 20 to 16.
So you just feed that part of the instruction those bits as the address for the read register too.
And then we know that the destination register is 15 to 11, so that's also in the address for the
right register.
We also need to provide a Ridge right to 1:00 because we want to write to the register file.
And here is also the ALU and we need to consider some, you know, this, the ALU operation such that
you can select what operation you want to do.
So there should be 3 or some number of bits here based on the number of operations that you're
supporting in the Lu to, to basically select the instructions.
So here we need to coordinate nicely such that in the Lu you do addition.
OK.
And then this, yeah, these two read data is OK.
So you you output this source register to the to the Lu and then the result of the Lu we're going to
be right back to your register file.
OK, so this data pass works well for our type now.
So here is also an example how we can design ALU like depending on the functional code.
I think is actually you've seen that in your in the combination logic, but based on the function
code, you can have different functions to process.
So this actually quite recall for you.
So now we want to also add another instruction type which is I type ALU instructions.
So we already have our type ALU instructions, but now we want to have support for I type ALU
instructions.
So in I type you have two register operands and one immediate.
So here's an example of the meet assembly like add I add immediate and the.
Machine and coding of it.
So the up code basically is based on the the first six bits here like not the first, the the most
significant the six bits.
And then you have this Rs and RT and this immediate which needs to be which will get sign extend to
32 bits.
And then, for example, in this instruction add I, this immediate we're going to be added to Rs and
there will be a store to RT.
So RT is going to be our destination register in the in the I type ALU functions instructions.
So the now you want to complete our datapath such that be able to run both R and I type ALU
instructions.
So this is what we can do with our type.
But now The thing is that the destination Register here if for the for the I type this needs to be
instructions in this region should be the address of RT.
So that's why we need to add a multiplexer here such that it can select based on the which part,
which part of the instruction is going to be the address for your destination register.
If it is R type, it's going to be instruction 15 to 11.
If it is I type is going to be instruction 20 to 60.
So by adding this multiplexer, you make sure that you can support the registered destination address
for the for these R type and I type area instructions.
And the selector of this multiplexer is going to be like is I type.
If the instruction is I type, then you just you go with this.
Yeah, it's I type, you go with 20 to 16.
If it's our type, you need to go with 15 to 11.
And then also here, So in I type, you need to operate one of the operand is actually coming from the
immediate right.
So here is the immediate value.
So basically you just from the instruction, the the 1st 16 bits of the instruction, instruction 15
to 0 is going to be is going to fit to the sign extent logic and it's going to be sign extended to
32 bits.
And then here the L you need, you need to consider another multiplexer here such that you can decide
or select based on this whether or not you want to get the source from the immediate value or you
want to get from the register file.
So there should be this multiplexer and then you can select based on the fact that this instruction
is immediate.
Sorry, I type or R type makes sense.
So by adding these two multiplexer, we can be happy and we can now support these two instructions.
Yeah, so but just to give you to jog your memory, we also had have seen that kind of things in also
in prior lectures when we were showing this addition logic in LC3.
So you've seen this Sinex and logic and also multiplexer.
So in the end we are covering MIPS micro architecture, but a lot of processors are actually
following the same principles.
There are different multiplexer here and there in order to control the how your data flow in the in
the in the processor micro architecture in the processor data paths.
OK, so any question now we get to data movement instructions.
The first instruction we want to we are looking at is load instruction.
So load for byte word yeah, exactly load for byte word which is considered LW.
So with that we are essentially we give 2 operands, 2 register operands and one immediate.
So how it works is that this Register here which is considered as a source register is going to be
added with this immediate sign extent immediate and then that value is going to be your the address
that you based on that you want to access your memory.
So you add this S0 with sign extent 8 and then that generates the address to the memory.
You access your memory with that address and the output of the memory you you need to write it back
to this RT register which is here S3.
So yeah.
And that's also the semantics which you can also take a look.
So how we can support this load word instruction So the the RT which is?
Which is the destination register is already fine because we already added it for the immediate I
type ALU instruction.
So this multiplexer is good.
But now the there are two different things here.
Actually there is this thing that the output of the ERU, it doesn't need to, it's it's not going
through this write back.
The output of ALU will go to the address of the memory and then you need to add the connection from
the output of the memory to your this write back boss.
So that's why there should be a multiplexer here essentially here just such that you decide based on
the output of the ALU or the output of the memory, OK.
And similarly also more or less similar for the storage structure, you essentially you have two
registers again for one of them, which is a source, you, you use it to generate the address that
you want to store.
And then the other instruction will be used as the data that you want to store and to write in the
memory.
So again, so here also the right register.
So yeah, one thing that which I forget also is that in load word, because in the end you want to
write to the register file, this read write also needs to be 1 and from the memory, because you
want to load from the memory, you you assert the mem read signal to 1 and then you put mem write
also to 0 because you don't want to, you want only to read from the memory.
However, in the store, so you set this arrange right to 0.
So by doing that actually you make this right register address be like don't care.
So you don't care anymore because you don't want to store right.
There might be some address in the right register which you don't care as long as this arrange right
is 0 because you are not writing to the register file.
And then the output of the ALU again is going to be the address to access the memory.
Howard, what you want to write to the memory, it should actually be fit to this write data.
So that would be actually the the another read value from the register file.
So this are this one, the first one is Rs, the other one is RT which you read it from from here and
then this you need to provide the pass to the to the memory as the store value.
And based on that, you can actually store that register in your memory.
Also you need to activate the memory right in order to write to the memory.
Makes sense.
OK.
So with that when we want to have loaded store data paths, essentially what we want to do, we need
to do is actually, yeah, essentially we need to provide this pass from this read output to the
memory for the right data.
And also this this read data is coming to the right data.
Actually there should be another pass.
Yeah, exactly data pass for non control flow instructions.
So this output of the ALU or output of the memory, these two needs to be multiplexed in order to
decide about the the the data that you want to write to your register file.
If the instruction is load word, you're going to select these three data.
If the instruction is, let's say ALU instructions like arithmetic operations, for example, the R
type ALU or I type ALU, you essentially select this line in order to restore to the register file.
And you need to basically generate all these multiplexer selectors essentially.
So these are like control signals that you need to generate in order to make sure that you handle
the flow of your data nicely in the data pass Makes sense, very good.
Feel free to ask questions.
But I know these are not that hard when you when we go over them.
But if you have some questions, feel free to ask of course.
OK, so now let's get to control flow instructions.
So you meet for example, we have jump instruction which is unconditional branch or jump in which you
can see like jump target and the the encoding of this instruction, if you remember it, there is so
you have 6 bits of up code and there is this 26 bits for immediate.
So what you do it as a semantics of this instruction is that.
The the the target PC is going to be the the four most significant bit of the PC +4.
So you do PC Plus four and then the most significant the the four most significant bits of that you
you will concatenate to the immediate 26 bits and then you also add these two zero at the end.
The reason is that in MIPS all instructions are 4 bytes, but the memory is actually byte
addressable.
So we know that all the instruction address is going to be is divided, can be divided by 4 because
all instructions are 4 bytes.
So that's why in order to save a space, in order to increase actually the let's say the region that
you can jump to.
So we don't put this 00 in the in the instruction.
We know that they're going to be added anyway because all the instruction needs to be divided,
should be should be divisible by 4 essentially.
And then after calculating this target, you need to load it to the program counter.
So the data pass in order to support unconditional jump is that so this is a normal way that we
calculate the next PC, right?
So the output of the PC is going to be added by 4:00 and then we generate the the next PC.
But that's a normal way.
But sometimes we have jump instruction and we should see how we can do it.
So first we need to make sure that we don't we do not harm any other parts of the data pass.
So this jump instruction which is unconditional, we are not doing anything, for example, in the
register file or we are not doing anything in the memory.
So that's why we make sure that, for example, we apply zero to the right, right enable of the
register file.
We apply zero to the memory, right, in order to make sure that we don't write to these memories and
other signals are actually don't care.
Like we don't care what we do in the ALU, we don't care what we do, like what we select here in this
multiplexer, we don't care because we don't hard anything essentially.
So that's also very important to design your control signals.
You need to make sure that when your instruction doesn't need to deal with other parts of the data
paths, you should not harm those parts of data paths.
So that's very important when you design your control signals.
So how we support jump instruction essentially you need to concat your the four most significant
bits of the PC and then you also input the instruction, the immediate part of the instruction which
is zero to 25 as a 26 bits.
So you can't get this and also the four most significant bits of the PC.
And then you generate the output with with also with 00.
And then you generate the output as a target.
And then there should be multiple extra here again to decide what would be the the next PC value.
Are you going to decide?
Are you going to select this jump address or PC Plus 4 essentially?
Which we know that for jump instruction is unconditional.
So whenever you have unconditional jump instruction, you're going to always select this target
address which is coming from this concatenation logic.
So based on that you input to the PC in order to do the next address.
So now question is, is this correct just to?
Test is this data pass correct to support jump instruction?
I mean, at least you can say yes or no, right?
I guess you know that the answer is no, but yeah, then then I would ask why?
I have a feeling that my can have strange feedback situation.
No, that's not the problem.
So the four, the four most significant bits that we need to concat is actually coming from PC +4.
So you need to actually feed it from this output the foremost most significant bit.
So when you do PC +4 they may affect the form MSP.
Bits of the instructions.
So that's why it's important to feed it from there and then you can do it.
So that's actually one of the big mistake that people can easily make, you know, when they design
data pass.
So it's important that we always care and focus a lot on the semantics of the instructions to not
make these mistakes.
OK.
There are also some other jumps that we don't cover like jump register, jump register, jump and link
and also jump and link register.
So here in this slide I provide the semantic of them like for example, jump and link register is
very important for your for function calls.
So when you want to call a function, you essentially you jump to a, to a, to a value which is
defined by the source register.
So that function address, the function called the address needs to be stored in a register and then
based on that register value, you're going to jump to that basic location.
But at the same same time also you have this written address register which you store the next PCPC
plus 4IN that written address which going to be used when you want to return from that function.
So remember in your for example, C programming, when you do this return something, you're returning
to the the point that you called your function, right?
So that's why, for example, MIPS also have these instructions jump and link.
And so these instructions are also not that hard to support.
But these for example, data pass does not support it.
You can think about it how you can update this data pass in order to support these instructions
maybe and also this kind of a MIPS CHEAT SHEET, which you can, if you're interested, you can check.
There are many instructions that in the end your data path should be able to support all of them.
OK, so another important branches are actually conditional branches.
So The thing is that for conditional branches, you also need to do some operations.
You need to do some computation to decide whether or not you are going to, you will take the branch
or or the branch is going to be not taken.
So one of them is branch, equal branch if equal.
So you provide the two register considering as a source of brands.
And essentially if there's two registers are equal, then you branch, if not, you don't branch.
So the semantics of the instruction is that we we check.
So first we actually calculate the target address.
The target address is actually PC +4.
So we always actually calculate based on plus PC +4.
So it's actually PC Plus 4 + extent immediate.
So there is an immediate here, which is actually in this concept, in this instruction, we can
consider as offset.
So in these conditional branches, your instruction addressing is actually instruction relative.
So in jump, for example, is actually also a little bit relative because you are using the four most
significant bits.
But in branch if equal and also branch not if not equal, you are basically you give the offset to
the instruction like from this point of the instruction to where I want to go.
And then you just give the offset.
You just encode the offset in the in the instruction.
So that's why we call it immediate offset here.
So that offset also needs to be sign extent and then you need to multiply it by 4 for the same
reason that I mentioned in the jump.
All instruction needs to be divisible by 4.
So that's why we times also to four.
And then you calculate this target address.
If these two sources are equal, then you jumped or branch essentially to this target address.
Otherwise, you just go to the PC +4 and there are different variations of it like branch.
This one is branch.
If we call branch not equal, branch less, less than or equal than 0, branch greater than 0 on so on
and so forth.
So how can we support this conditional branch?
So I will basically leave it also to you as a homework if you're interested to design it.
I mean, it's actually also so mentioned in your book.
You can check it but just give you some idea.
Essentially in this instruction you need to increase, basically have more output, have more input to
this multiplexer.
So this multiplexer needs to be bigger.
Because now it needs to decide based on more things, you know, PC +4 or jump target address or this
relative addressing which is for BEQ, for example.
And then you need to use this PC Plus 4.
Here is also your immediate which you do sign extent and then you shift left by two and added with
PC +4 and that's your branch target which is coming through this multiplexer in ALU.
Also you need to do this operation.
So basically the two source operand, you read it from the register file and then you do this
subtract for example operation.
So why is it subtract?
Because when you want to check equality, for example, you can just subtract these two registers.
And if the output is 0, then there is actually out usually MIPS and some other ILUAILUS.
You have one output which is Z.
So when the Z is asserted, meaning that the value of ALU output is 0 essentially.
So that's why you can actually do subtract and then this.
You use this output signal of Z from the ALU to decide whether or not you need to take the branch.
Sounds good.
OK, yeah, here also I want to foreshadow something which we're going to see more than in the branch
in the branch prediction lecture.
But essentially MIPS actually implements, I would say bad idea, which is delayed branch semantics.
So your data path should be.
Also should be able to run delayed branching semantics.
And what is the delayed branch semantics?
Is that so in mix, whenever you have a branch instruction, the next instruction should always be
executed also.
So that is called delayed branch instructions.
So the way basically you can think of, OK, I have a branch instruction and then I will add another
instruction which going to be OK to execute no matter if I'm going to take that branch or not.
So that's a job for the compiler to find those instructions to put it.
But that's makes it very bad idea because most of the time it's not easy to find those instructions
and you may get end up putting no pressures.
Yes, the reason for that because of pipeline, yes, we're going to get to that later in the
pipelining lectures and also in branch prediction.
Yeah, same question.
OK, OK, so putting everything together, we're going to get to this beautiful design which we have
all these, you know, these addition logic, these multiplexer in order to calculate the, you know,
the the next PC.
Also the multiplexer as the input of the ALU, the the multiplexer for the, for the right back and so
on and so forth.
And there is this control logic with all these orange signals, which basically this control logic
generates how we can, how we can make sure that data pass, you know, execute our instructions
correctly.
So if I want to go over it for one of a few of them, for example, for example, for the branch
instruction for the conditional branch.
So in MIPS, actually they they call it, they usually say branch and jump, meaning that branches are
always conditional and jump are unconditional.
That's why here we have in the control logic, we have output of branch, OK.
But in order to be clear, this branch is actually output saying that my instruction is conditional
branch, OK.
So that's why we have this essentially output of jump, meaning that the instruction is jump or
unconditional branch or the instruction is conditional branch.
OK, so when you want to execute or control the execution of branch, if equal the control logic
generate this branch conditional branch.
So if their instruction is branch, conditional branch and then the the condition of the the output
of the ALU, which actually you can think of this Z output signal, which I already explained.
So in a you, you subtract these two registers that you you want to check if the output is 0, then
they're going to be 1 here.
OK, so you just and these two.
And if these two are basically if the result of this and is one, that means that you have this
conditional branch and you want to take the branch.
So that's why you need to select basically this output from this edition which.
Coming from the PC Plus four added by sign extent immediate shifted by two.
So that's the output.
So you selected here and then it gives goes to another multiplexer which you again you need to
select it.
So here also you you always select this this line unless you have an instruction which is jump.
So if your instruction is jump which is unconditional branch, you always select basically this line
number one.
But other than that you select zero so that you select here and then this goes back to your PC.
OK, so you can actually go over this data pass design to see different instructions how they are
implemented.
But that being said, there are some instructions that they are omitted here also like jump and link,
jump register and jump and link register.
OK, question.
So now let's also quickly look at the control logic, which we already explained it actually more or
less.
But it's good to also go over it a little bit with a bit more detail.
So we want to have hard wire controls for all these control signals and we need to be able to run
all these instructions.
Essentially we need to have a control logic to generate all these control output.
So one way of thinking about it is that you come up with a big true stable and then you have all
these control signals as the output and the input of that true stable is actually your up code,
function code and so on and so forth, right?
But that true stable is going to be quite big, which is a bit impractical, you know, to implement.
So that's why people are actually working on it usually with some semantics saying that these for
example, this destination which is the control signal used from from this multiplexer.
So this so they come up with this semantics when DE asserted and when asserted.
So this when GPR right select according to RT meaning that instruction is 22, instructions 20 to 16.
So this Reg this needs to be de asserted when asserted.
For example when the when basic based on the encoding this address is coming from the destination
register in the instruction format which is instruction 15 to 11 and then so based on that then you
need to come up with the equation.
So here is actually easy.
Basically whenever you are, you have our type.
You want to have it asserted, so that's why you say that.
When of course.
It's siegel and.
Opcode is 0.
So basically we we set Reg this to one for other than other also control signal.
You can have similar methodology like ALU source which is used here.
OK.
So essentially you can see that when de asserted is when the second ALU input from the second
general purpose register file report OK.
And when asserted is when the second ALU input is coming from the sign extended 16 bit immediate.
So that's the semantic.
And then the equation is that you can say that OK.
So when asserted essentially when OP code is not 0, meaning that we are not doing R type and also
when the OP code is not branch equal and also when the OP code is not branch not equal.
So with all these other than that, basically we need to assert this signal.
For example, because in in in branch equal and also branch not equal, you again need to compare 2
red registers.
So you still need to have two registers.
Other than that you go with the immediate port immediate date.
OK, So I leave it and the rest for you to go over it.
It's not that hard.
So once you come up with this equation, then you can come up with the logic to support that equation
essentially.
So let's quickly also recap again.
So in R type ALU, for example, the way we can run it, essentially we read instruction and then
basically in this picture we can see, you know the flow of all these multiplexers.
So this instruction is this is going to be selected for the right register is going to Reg right is
going to be 1, and then this output is going to be selected.
The function code needs to be decided and then you don't need to touch memory.
That's why all the control signal, the memory are 0 and the right back is actually coming from the
output of the Lu.
So that's why you have this selection and for the for the PC for the next PCs you are doing PC Plus
4IN R type Alu.
So that's why you're selecting here PC Plus four.
And then clearly is also not a jump instruction.
So you go like this and then you update.
So that's R type in I type you do more or less the same.
The difference is here that you select the destination register from this line and then also this
multiplexer that you select immediate for I type ALU for load words, for example instruction, you
select here the right register and then here also you need to select this immediate.
So that's the line for that.
And then you need to access the memory.
So that's why you you need to control the signals of the memory.
So you give one because you want to load this read memory is 1.
So you read from the memory and then you need to control this multiplexer such that you store the
output of the memory to the register file, OK and so on and so forth.
You can also check this store word just to give you some perspective here also for a store word, for
example, we don't store in the register file, right?
So we put 0 as a right enable of the register file.
So which means that this multiplexer, whatever it does, it's don't care for us.
So it's good to know about these don't carries because that gives you simplicity.
You know how to simplify the hardware for that.
OK.
And also the branch instruction, the conditional branch.
So here it shows the you know, the the the the data pass or the flow of the data when the branch is
not taken.
So, yeah, everything is this, yeah, essentially you, you need to do this, these two read registers,
you do the operation ALU and then based on that, you generate this control signal.
And here also you need to go with the PC Plus 4 because you don't want to take the branch.
And then when you want to take the branch, you essentially get differences here.
OK, so it's here it's important that basically some control signals are dependent on the processing
of data.
So it's not always that we decode the instruction and we generate control signals and then we are
done.
In some cases, especially branch instructions, these control signals actually also needs to be
defined based on the analysis that we are doing based on the execution.
And for the jump instruction, essentially everything, all these are don't care because we don't.
And also we put zero to not harm anything.
So we don't harm register file, we don't harm memory.
And again, this multiplexer is also don't care for us, only here this multiplexer we provide.
So basically we need to provide the address from this line which is the target address from PC Plus
4 concatenation of four bits, 4 most significant bits, the instruction and also that 20 that we
add.
So basically this comes here and then we select it and then we move back to the PC.
And then the control box actually can be combinational logic which is hard wire control.
So basically implement all these equation as a hard wire control or can be sequential logic meaning
that you have a memory and then you put all these control signals and in that memory and based on
the based on the instruction essentially and also some other controlled data you fetch from that
memory in order to update your control signals.
So this is called controller store and actually modern processor are combining these two way
basically in the design and also both of them can be used for single cycle processors.
OK, so this is what we have reviewed in your book.
Actually also they have a little bit different design, which if you want to check more, you can also
check it.
So this final design from your book.
And you can also go over different instructions.
So here for example, is the how we can do this load word instruction.
It's essentially the same thing in the end.
So we basically provide the PC and then the part of the instruction.
And then you need this also sign extend immediate.
You add the ALU in order to add this source operands and then you generate the address for the
memory, you access the memory and then the read data you basically write back to the memory.
So there's not much difference.
There are some difference how we handle the the branch instruction, which you can also check if
you're more interested.
Your book actually goes with the also this kind of a true stable design, which we can also check if
you're interested.
Yeah.
So that would be your assignment to go over these slides and think about how we build our datapaths,
which is not that in the end, it's not a magic.
And I think by now you can see that this wasn't very complicated.
OK, Let me check the time.
So we still have some time.
So I'm going to start a little bit evaluation of this architecture because we've already done that
actually in that foreshadow slide that we go over the performance evaluation metric.
But basically we want to ask a single cycle micro architecture, is this a good idea or design?
And when is this a good design and when is this a bad design?
And, and how can we design A better micro architecture, which we're going to see next week when we
get to the multi cycle processor.
So remember about this performance analysis basics.
So in the basically when we want to evaluate the performance, essentially we want to see how fast is
my program and how fast are my instructions.
So that's why then the series of instructions that we are executing are important and then the
processor based on that I say this, the CPI, the cycles for instruction and also the clock
frequency of the the clock cycle is important.
I'm going a bit fast here because we already discussed it in that slide.
So there is this general formula that essentially this N number of instruction times CPI times T
which is the clock cycle or you can think of times one over frequency essentially.
So in single cycle every instruction takes one cycle to execute.
So the CPI is a strictly one by by definition.
And how long each instruction takes is determined by how long the slowest instruction takes to
execute.
So we have many instructions and these instructions might have completely different latencies.
But then you need to calculate the longest latency and then based on that your set your clock
frequency.
So we need to do this all these phases which we actually in our system in our data pass, we have
moved them to the five steps.
So we can have different numbers for all steps of these.
I mean the in the micro architecture.
So let me go over this example for example.
We know that we can.
And assume that memory units like read or write they take 200 picosecond, ALU and others take 100
picosecond.
Register for it takes 50 picosecond and other logic or write delay are 0 picosecond.
Yeah for simplicity.
And then based on different instructions like regarding what steps they are going through, you can
actually calculate the delay of them like R type, you need to fetch instructions so this 200
picosecond.
And then you need to do access the register file, which is 50 picoseconds.
And then you do the ALU which is 100 picosecond.
And then you do the write back, which is 50.
And again you're going to get to the delay of 400 picoseconds.
The load word instruction, which is the longest 1 you need to fetch and then decode.
You go to the ALU and then you access the memory and then you do the write back which is 600
picoseconds.
So now you can see that the longest one is actually load word because it goes through all these
steps.
It's kind of also intuitive.
So with that you need to, for example, in this example you to consider that your clock cycle should
be long enough to accumulate 600 picosecond combination of latency.
So you can go over these slides also again at as your homework if you're interested.
But essentially you can consider all these numbers here and then check different instructions when
they go over these data paths essentially and then calculate the numbers.
OK.
And for control logic, actually we consider that there is no latency in our design, but that's food
you're for thought essentially because control logic can be also on the critical pass at some
point.
If you if you want to support thousands of instructions, then the control logic can be very
complicated to be on the critical pass.
OK, so I think I will leave it from this point.
We will continue next week.
I'd like to also to mention before saying have a nice weekend, I want to say happy Persian New Year
also, which happened just 15 minutes ago.
So if you're interested to learn more about Persian New Year fundamentals principle behind it,
because there has been a lot of mathematics and physics behind it.
So you can check if you're interested.
So have a nice weekend and see you next week.